练习 1-15：语调变化。注意：实际词语
Exercise 1-15 Inflection Notice how the meaning changes while the actual words
本身不变，意思却会改变。第一句：“不是我说他偷了钱。”别人说的。第二句：
stay the same. 1. I didn't say he stole the money. Someone else said it. 2. I
“不是我说他偷了钱。”这完全不是真的。第三句：“不是我说他偷了
didn't say he stole the money. That's not true at all. 3. I didn't say he stole the
钱。”我只是暗示这种可能。第四句：“不是我说他偷了钱。”我
money. I only suggested the possibility. 4. I didn't say he stole the money. I
认为是别人拿走的。第五句：“不是我说他偷了钱。”也许他只是
think someone else took it. Five. I didn't say he stole the money. Maybe he just
借走了。第六句：“不是我说他偷了钱，而是别的钱。”
borrowed it. Six. I didn't say he stole the money, but rather some other money.
第七句：“不是我说他偷了钱。”他可能拿了珠宝。接下来解释。
Seven. I didn't say he stole the money. He may have taken some jewelry. I didn't say
“不是我说他偷了钱。”别人说的。确实有人这么说，但我
he stole the money. Someone else said it. It's true that somebody said it, but I
不是那个人。“不是我说他偷了钱。”这完全不是真的。有人
wasn't that person. I didn't say he stole the money. That's not true at all. Someone
指控我，我在为自己的清白抗辩。“不是我说他偷了
has accused me, and I'm protesting my innocence. I didn't say he stole the
钱。”我只是暗示这种可能。也许我暗示过，也许我写下了
money. I only suggested the possibility. Maybe I hinted it. Maybe I wrote it in
某种方式表明他偷了钱，但我没有说出口。“不是我说
some way I indicated that he stole the money, but I didn't say it. I didn't say
他偷了钱。”我认为是别人拿走的。我认为有人偷了钱，
he stole the money I think someone else took it. I think someone stole the money
只是不是你怀疑的那个人。“不是我说他偷了钱。”也许他
only not the person you suspect did it I didn't say he stole the money. Maybe he
只是借走了。我承认他拿了钱，但我认为动机不同。“不是我说
just borrowed it I agree that he took it, but I think his motive was different I
他偷了钱，而是别的钱。”我们同意他偷了
didn't say he stole the money, but rather some other money we agree that he stole
一些钱，但不认为是这笔钱。“不是我说他偷了钱。”他
some money but I don't think it's this money. I didn't say he stole the money. He
可能拿了珠宝。我们同意他是小偷，但认为他偷了
may have taken some jewelry. We agree that he's a thief, but we think he stole
不同的东西。注意，在这些句子的前半部分，除了语调之外，
different things. Notice that in the first half of these sentences, nothing changes
没有任何变化。
but the intonation.